let's talk a little that I think you
probably know you've all done the same
thing but I thought we can start
obviously it's translated differently
and we are getting into that we really
regarded his assumption because in its
nature you if it's if people think who
put on his attachment or what was it on
clinging grasping grasping again it
applies me reacting to things in a
certain appropriative manner but loop
Alanna is what precedes that you
appropriating things and reorient minds
the result of the OPA Donna it's not
Europa Donna in other words you can't
it's not on the level of choice for you
to stop clinging so that's why whenever
you say clinging or grasping well at
least for me kind of sounds like oh I'm
clinging to this and I'm grasping that
that's always the result of open that
means it's more of an assumption you
took something for granted you took for
granted that you can own this and now
you're exercising your attitude and
actions towards ownership but you will
never do that if you fully understand
that it's unknowable to begin with if
you free yourself from that assumption
so if we take assumption and for the
contemplation what would be how would
you describe its properties say well
it's practically sensuality is is an
assumption so how would you describe
that why why why is it an assumption well for
why why why is it an assumption well for
me like something that's an exam
they're kind of underlies everything
so I guess in terms of sensuality it
would be she's not understanding not
seeing not examining what what
sensuality is so what is it
sensuality you have you arrived at
assumptions for the example of of that
which being assumed in this case
centrality so what is sensuality you
kind of attitude towards the things that
you can bodily but things like again
let's try to be more regular than a
sense of done
there's only for a theoretical answer
more like imagine you experience of
sensuality craving for a taste so
feeling pulled towards something like
yeah thank so describe that so it's a
form of pool yeah
can you have centrality for example
without without a desire no I think to
be honest I think karma karma karma
comes from the verb karma it which means
visit design mmm it's just desire that's
what it does it sense desire it's
decided desire all the senses senses in
some of the senses so you cannot
possibly engage in in any experience of
sensuality that's the course and show
thing without having desire that
underlying it so then the assumption of
sensuality must be in their level as
well but as we described before
sensuality means perverting order of
things sorry assumption it means to open
sorry assumption it means to open
enemies perverting all the things owning
the unknowable assuming the sense of
self outside of this
which is a contradiction in terms
because you're experiencing that so you
be you maintaining an assumption way but
you think you can think outside of the
experience as a whole that's why it's an
assumption because it cannot be done yet
you not clarify be very good you keep
doing it so then the design being also
another type of OPA Donna shares the
same nature it will must be sharing the
same nature isn't it because desire
basically involves but this given
situation I mean this this basically
like so I sing here not having this
taste but with that taste as a
possibility mm-hmm let's make it even
more narrow
okay would you have desired if things
are not pleasant no that's it Roger yeah
it's a desire for pleasure and then he
then the pleasure also basis for your
desire the pleasure for wanting pleasure
is the basis for the design how would
you be wanting pleasure unless that's
already felt pleasantly how would you
know it's Pleasant so unless you're
feeling yet there's the thing so that's
what I wanted to say that basically the
possibility of pleasure is given to me
it's basically I have been subjected to
this this possibility for pleasure
mm-hmm not seeing that that possibility
for pleasure is just something else that
I've been subjected to I think let's go
for I go for that and how is that
possibly the brother felt that let that
possibility well it depends if it's not recognized
well it depends if it's not recognized
as something that I've just been
subjected to then it'll be felt as
pleasant but if you see that it's just
another thing that I have been subjected
to just like this
lack of that this feeling I have no
having that thing mm-hmm whether I'm
subjected since that feeling of that
feeling it's all just if you think if
you recognize it on the level of on that
level of it's all just something that I
have been hit with then well let me see
the next amount of place sure sure but
I'm not going about like oh when you
make the effort to recognize it just the
experience of the recent project of
pleasure how's that felt the experience
of the arisen prospector pleasure
pleasure sensual pleasure yes so so you
are not engaging your senses are not
engaging with particular pleasure but
now there is a possibility for them to
do so yeah how's that felt does fells
pleasurable well actually no it's felt
as painful in the sense that I'm I want
I need to do this but there's a pleasure
involved in that exactly
but which which is the one that comes
first one that comes first well as
that's always the thing it depends I as
you see it so if you if you don't
recognize if you don't see no it doesn't
have been like you don't like as I
explained about the up or down of
antibody for example it doesn't depend
how you see it
you always keep assuming your sense
yourself outside of the experience as a
whole outside of the five agree it's
whether you see it or not yeah doesn't
matter that's the mistake so once you
start seeing it you and do it and then
there is no other way you can't assume
it again because now you saw it as
impossible so since design shares the
same nature so that's what we're trying
to get to the bottom of where is that
nature contained so so which is which is
that which comes first in the case of a
recent prospect of sensual desire or
rather central pursuit sensual pleasure
is it that it's unpleasant first and
then prospect of pleasure comes over it
or prospect of pleasure is first but
then that's felt unpleasantly which one
is it
again let's back to the practical
example go back to play you have now
possibility for a pleasant taste meet
something how is that felt I guess I
feel like ordinarily it would be okay
but now when you stop being devoted now
we stop thinking about you realize that
well that it was a pain involved in not
having it and we just live comes first
visit the pain or the the absence of
pleasure of the absence of pleasure
right now is that is that's more
fundamental than the initial kind of
buzz you get from the possibility yeah
so if the absence of this possible
pleasure this particular food is first
felt unpleasantly what would be the
necessary basis then for you to go for
that pleasure to know see that time to
know sure to cover over there so in the
in that way any form of engagement of
sense desires requires you to ignore how
you feel thirst yeah of the fundamental
feeling okay yeah so the pathway or jump
are say of following the the sense
desire is always open
it's not me blocking it but the fact is
that that's felt unpleasantly first and
you ignore it in order to go down there
way that's why it's a mistake can I say
is like it's you're saying it's first
belters unpleasant fundamentally you're
gonna say it's like it's more the more
general feeling oh yeah I don't mean
first felt as in there when you chase
the pleasure the pain disappears so
there is a pleasure pain remains
throughout which is why the pain is the
motivation of your sensuality so it's
like there's a pleasure this buzz of the
possibility of having that taste but
that pleasure is contained within is
more general
displeasure this sure yeah that's what
keep talking about more fundamental yeah
so the more fundamental discomfort will
be of the prospect of pleasure remains
throughout your engaging with the
pleasure which is why you keep engaging
with the pleasures and not being mindful
what helps you to ignore the more
fundamental pain yeah well that's the
thing there is no starting point for the
there is no starting point for the
ignorance in regard to anything
including sensuality and because there
is no starting point of this type of
ignoring people there is also no
starting point for their assumption the
prospect of pleasure is the pleasure
that they already delight in that they
engage with they they pursue and so on
so they don't see the underlying pain
that's constantly present with it
simultaneously to the same extent but on
a more fundamental level so then through
your own engagement with sensuality you
keep obscuring more and more that which
underlines it which is pain and that's
why sensuality is insatiable because
pain is here on one level your acts
toward sin surely can be on a domain of
sensuality cannot do anything about the
fact that it's felt painfully before you
act so then no amount of action
satisfaction desire proliferation the
the extent of your no amount of
restraint would an automatically
obviously restraint is necessary to you
to start that questioning backwards so
to speak and not keep chasing the sense
objects but it won't tell you to that
mode you know unless you understand it
you won't be free from it because again
sensuality is not engagement with the
objects of your senses sensualities
assumption it's a new Perdana which
means there is some perversion of the
order there that's why sensuality is
there now that perversion is maintained
through your engagement based on that
ignorance engaging with sense objects
but once you remove the ignorance and
engagement with sense objects can often
do sensuality animal but that obviously
means that the extent of your old
engagement there was based on ignorance
we'll be significantly reduced such as
our hand cannot possibly have sexual
intercourse or think about central Ohio
I'm gonna next day and then this and you
just unthinkable for him but now let's
make it even more accurate if sensuality
is full first felt unpleasantly
let's nothing don't think about the
prospect of the pleasure now just think
about the pain since we revealed it yeah
how you're not having these things I
could have anything yeah any nature of
painful feeling yeah
what are its characteristics painful
feeling yeah Oh what would what is the
corrected what are the characteristics
of the experience as a whole that is
subjected to a painful feeling there and
give us that it's something that you
subjected to okay so I can only discover
that hey has already enjoyed what else
do these come have no control over it
being there okay so what is the natural
response so the no ordinary response
would be if you were to not understand
that that pain isn't yours
the ordinary responses to say I don't
wanna well what would be an honor Nogami
response how they wanna yeah so not
wanting pain yeah undesirable exactly
but soon only because you're not
recognizing that it's gone yeah no
that's fine let's [\h__\h] it let's just
stick with the pain it's basically
undesirable and as the Buddha said in
every painful feeling there is craving
to get a little bit unless you
completely free from craving and how is
that prospects of getting rid of pain
felt thankfully is it I will see okay
well so you subjected to pain and
there's a paucity of pensee see missing
man okay so the boys are the possibility
of that pain not being there well
doesn't it but what is the pleasure of
that I was thinking as
we are under threat here okay what is
then the pleasure in that prospect
what is pleasant of that pain opener so
then the pleasure of the prospect of not
having this pain is pleasant to the
extent that this is painful
yes it's not a separate pleasure no it's
a back of the same coin it is yeah so
it's one phenomenal way of looking at
the other Walter it's one phenomenon
there yeah because every presence of
this implies the absence of this
whatever that is so presence of pain
implies absence of pain yeah this same
pain presence of pain is felt
unpleasantly simultaneous to that to the
possibility of its absence is felt
pleasantly yeah just an Ardex pain and
that possibility of pleasure are they
separate completely bound up with each
other exactly yeah so if you look at one yeah
exactly yeah so if you look at one yeah
you can say that's what I'm feeling but
if you look together but again from
where do they come from they come from
the same thing yeah
yeah so it's it's basically one
phenomenon with two sides took like two
sides of one coin literally so you can't
have one without having the other yep
and it's on that level that sensuality
happens the assumption of it the wrong
order the outside interest when you put
the pleasure in case of art Avada you
put that first because it's more
pleasant because it shelters you from
the daily all sorts of anxiety that you
are not in control of your life not to
control of your senses so you assumed an
external point of view to this
experience in the hold its kind of
unaffected despite whatever is happening
in this experience but that's a
completely cheated assumption that's
almost like developed for the purpose of
kind of covering it up covering the
issues up defense mechanism so to speak
and that's that's always the principle
of every opener by the way avoiding pain
that's why you develop
assumptions because they shelter you
from admitting that you were subjected
to pain we can go into the other of
bananas as well and you'll see it's
gonna be the same principle like seal
about the para mas my virtue my duty not
my responsibility to make it my virtue
my duty yeah I'm just I'm just dropping
this in so you can connect okay well
let's go back to the three that we said
so the two sides of the same coin can I
just say so it would be the same if
there's a pleasant feeling yeah that
Pleasant feeling the presence of a
pleasant feeling implies the lack of
that pleasant feeling yeah which would
be painful and you know you can you
assume us but you you put the you put
the possibility but generally one would
emphasize the pleasure no no see like
wait again imagine practically you're
subjected to some sensual pleasure right
now it takes effort for you to not crave
for more of it it takes effort for you
to go against the grain and stay and
appreciate what you have and enjoy it
because if you don't make the effort the
mind wants more because more pleasure
means this is painful say pain is
painful absence of pain is more
pleasurable you put that absence of pain first on
you put that absence of pain first on
the basis within the container of that
it's painful first so that's why that's
why we're started by asking you general
what is first in cases in Charlotte it's
always that is its container that is its
fundamental purpose and then you realize
that no amount of engagement with
sensuality as I said doesn't matter how
far down the senses you go the
motivation the actual pleasure that you
feel on account of central engagements
is the pleasure of avoiding pain that
still with you not the pleasure of you
touching things tasting things because
if the pleasure were contained in touch
taste smell sight it will always be
pleasant to the same extent and you
wouldn't even well you wouldn't be able
to think about it to be honest
because not having that means
non-engagement means absence of pleasure
absence of possibility of pleasure but
the fact that sometimes you can eat same
things and not experience pleasure on
account of it then eat eat things they
used to didn't cause you pleasure now
they're giving me pleasure means
pleasure is not in the sense objects nor
in the sense domain for that matter and
of course people have said that many
times like once you remove designer loss
from your mind he said he with the
target ah for the target that there are
beautiful things in the world he sees
this is beautiful this is ugly this is
agreeable this is the globe but it's
absolutely no sensuality whatsoever but
for most people when you think you think
sensuality means the the agree ability
of the sense objects but it doesn't
sensuality means perversion of your
perception you perceive second to come
first and that which is actually still
there is first you kind of perceive a
second and from that point of view you
realize how sensuality is not linear at
all because usually slightly the mind
would once it's subjected to that
assumption and the acts are the
Assumption would think I have a desire
then I act then I fulfill my desire
through engaging in this particular
sense object and then it's done yeah the
whole thing is within the painful
container of being subjected to it in
the first place and that is your sole
motivation but important precision here
is whenever there is a prospect of
pleasure that's felt pleasantly because
you'll be avoiding pain that pleasure is
the pleasure of the pain that you're
feeling it so that's why he you should
learn to see sensuality sense desires as
far as painful John now that you brought
it up the Buddha will always say he
understands the one who is free from
sensuality understands gratification the
danger and the escape that means full
understanding of the phenomenon so what
is that the gratification or the central
assumption the pleasure that which
pleasure the group the the gratification well the
the group the the gratification well the
extent of the pleasure that you can
possibly that is contained within done
that pain the extent of the pleasure
this can deal with the pain
yeah so so basic my Denix mom and dad
extent will be quite infinite no because
it's it's all within more general pain
so there is a pleasure and more
particular pleasure which is what you're
putting first sorry what somebody you
know somebody who's bound by sensuality
but first this pleasure not seeing that
that's bound up by and more fundamental
yeah but what is gratification that
pleasure did and how that the extent to
which that can the way but there's so
the gratification then is absence of
pain the gratification is absence of
pain
because it's a pain if there's a
pleasure that huh uh-huh
you know you have this prospects of
pleasure so let's put like this where is
that clarification
there is mortification yeah and needs to
be understood yeah where is it
anybody can chip in by the blindness to
ignoring of the pain well yeah
but again more more precisely now we are
not trying to undo the gratification
we're just trying to clarify this what
is it it is like the pleasure that
arises okay yeah so let's talk that the
pleasure arises on account of
possibilities of something which idea
own all the weight is underlined by the
pain sure yeah so why is that pleasure
Pleasant as I asked before there's a
qualified before why are you feeling
that prospect pleasantly because there's
because you're emphasizing because
you're getting reality so then that's
the gratification delighting in the
prospect of getting rid of the pain that
you don't question so you don't question
your ecosystems does originally
fundamentally present enduring pain yeah
you don't question it then there are
prospects to then like get away from it
and you will then automatically delight
in it and that's what I said
gratification is a delight in sense
objects it's your delight in the sense
object that's the gratification and
surely not engagement with the sense
objects even if you can get everything
you want yeah it's you delight thing
that's well that's already when you
start satisfying your desires because
you're you you accept the possibility of
satisfaction as in satisfaction over
there means escaping this present
enduring pain over here yeah sure sure
yeah it's it's on that level certainly
you might not be explicitly thinking
like clarify or it's a hope but yeah
the possibility of satisfaction he's
already delighted in that's already they
delight in the possibility of
satisfaction is will gratification order
it is and then dangers make exactly yeah
because you go down the domain that has
nothing to do with why you are going
down that domain because again there's a
whole irony contained in in any
assumption it's unpleasant there is an
experience as a whole you don't want
that pain so by not wanting that pain
you go to that which is painful because
that unpleasantly a pleasant there is an
experience the whole is easily
experience of sensuality as we described
it whenever there is a sense this is
first felt unpleasantly because you
don't want that unpleasurable and then
how do you think it's gonna be felt
unpleasantly so literally let scratching
the itch is if as I said each time you
engage you make it worse so then if you
clarify this you realize that sensuality
arises and it's felt unpleasantly and
you don't want pain
nobody wants pain and then you wring a
sensory strength is then the pleasure in
regards to that painful sensuality
upstanding from engaging with sensuality
is how you're gonna free yourself from
that pain of that sensuality and you
want to be free from it which is why you
keep engaging with it yeah that's why
sensuality pressures you because it's
underlined by the pain simultaneously
there and if you have any doubt about it
say no to yourself is got result and you
see the pressure that builds up why is
that why are you pressured where is the how
why are you pressured where is the how
is that pressure generated pressure
toward sense object
it's basically directly corresponds
simultaneously to the the extent of
craving that you maintain in regard to
the pain you remove the craving in
regard to the pain there is no pressure
towards a sense objects because the
prospect of the the pleasure of sense
object becomes non applicable
so that's why it's important like I keep
going back to this I don't know like we
can talk about later about the danger
and so on escape but it's all contained
in first then you can discern more
within the first principle and that's
that any degree of pleasure so imagine
actually physical engagement with
sensual pleasure amidst or physical
engagement with sensual pleasure the
pleasure ability pleasure ability of
physical engagement is actually the
delighting in freedom from
simultaneously enduring pain it's not
coming from the senses it's coming from
the pain so the freedom from that pain
yeah alleviation yeah to whatever extent
so again it's important to imagine it on
the right basis which is sensuality
central engagement sensual act pleasure
of it did you experience that you used
to experience did you sometimes still
might want to experience it doesn't
matter the extent of it that pleasure is
the alleviation of simultaneous enduring
pain it's not the pleasure that comes to
you through the senses it never leaves
that you keep assuming pleasure will be
external hoga you keep assuming pleasure
to be external to the present enduring
situation that is painful which is the
sensuality which is the assumption yeah
external how can you know how can you
know that this is pleasant while you're
not engaging with it so the pleasure
again imagine that sorry there is a
there is a prospect of sensual life
touch of a pleasant nature but you're
not touching it why is it felt
pleasantly that prospect cuz you if if
the pleasure is in the object of your
touch you know how can you know that
it's Pleasant now when you're not
touching it yet and again the argument
of oh because you have a memory from
before well it still doesn't work
because you are not elated on account of
memory you're related an account of the
future prospect of our
to touch this and yet that's felt
pleasantly before you touch it why
because it provides possibility no beak
well yeah okay yeah because the pain is
there so the pain is here claiming to
get rid of this pain is here which means
prosper that I might be able to is here
and then whatever pleasure are feeling
regards to anything out there is because
of this pain yeah pain is the peg
essential thing
yeah and that pain is the pleasure of
sensuality yeah so then when you go and
engage other things as pleasure of
sensuality is within it doesn't come
from it it stays within it that's the
part that's not trying to to hammer in
here because basically hammer there in
and there is no basis for assuming
external to this experience of
sensuality and you do it assume the
sense objects to be external to your
experience of desire which is why it's
insatiable because you perverted the
order and this domain of sense object
it's completely not applicable as I said
you're not even engaging with it yet you
are feeling pleasure and account of the
prospect of engaging with on the level
of the senses there is a desire there
and that desire is felt like you
delighting in it why because that desire
is fully within this pain that
simultaneously enduring to the same
extent so if you stop assuming that then
the pleasure of alleviating the pain
through following the desire is
contained external to the pain and the
desire you will stop diverting the order
in the same sense you stop assuming your
sense of self to be outside of your
experience as a whole you realize that's
inconceivable same principle of the same
padam panels are saying that the
pleasure is being external to the pain
is basically see okay they look you
already said it a thought of pleasure
might be external to the pain how would
you know that without engaging with that
where the pleasure might be which you're
not doesn't matter the extent that all
your thought as I said before like when
you say okay
I think I'm outside of this experience
the whole okay so I'm not excited this
experience is a horse up something
else's but then you but that can only be
the thought that's within this
experience as a whole
yeah but then this is the outside of
that thought which can only be within
it's the same principle in this case
once you start from the right level so
the pleasure that's outside of this
desire that has arisen is within this
desire has arisen because how can then
you feel it pleasantly that prospect of
that pleasure unless it's within this
desire and that's pretty much all you
need to clarify but all the way and it
will become well you will become unable
to think that pleasure is incense
objects the beautiful objects in the
world are the ones that have pleasure in
their and that's how sensuality falls
off does it mean you you wouldn't
recognize nice food or agreeable touch
but you certainly wouldn't crave for it
why because you don't crave for
gratuitous freedom from unpleasantness
because you don't crave to alleviate by
default of anything that's about this
combat simply cause that pleasure cannot
possibly undo no it's always exactly
it's it's always within that so that's
the thing so you're basically trying to
get rid of something by expecting
something more particular to get under
its roots sholde sure where it's
actually you that pain is there whether
you like or not you and again I don't
even know you want to be free from it
which is why you're engaged with yeah so
all you need to do is recognize that
it's painful first and you want to be
free from it yeah thus the best course
of action is to not engage with yeah but
then that means you now have to be able
to endure for as long as it takes not
acting out of the gratuitous assumption
of craving in regard to the unpleasant
enduring feeling but then even when you
have a thought a memory of previous
sensuality a thought of the future
sensuality and it's and the mind
delights in it you don't deny that you
just see it as included within this pain
and that the pleasure that's fair
even if you were to engage even when you
eat the food that's agreeable the
pleasure you're feeling is the
alleviation of the simultaneous enduring
pain there first
yeah basically we're not allowing it to
be assumed second yeah no no and he gets
assumed second when you when you become
careless when you basically know mindful
of the feeling yeah the general most at
the general level or when you lose sense
drink the past or the future
future prospect or the past experience
that's already like I said like that's
paying right here right now isn't it
like it's agent yeah that's another
thing you can you can clarify so how
would you know that the past prospects
were pleasant unless you're feeling them
now pleasurably how would you know that
the future prospect of engaging with the
particular sense objects oh why are you
feeling it planet pleasurably right here
right now so the extent doesn't matter
the extent how particular how committed
to a particular aspect of a sense object
are you deriving pleasure from any
pleasure derived from any sense action
is the pleasure of alleviating
simultaneously enduring pain it's not
the pleasure that comes from the object
and the reason why you have pressure to
engage with the object is because that's
how you give validity to the direction
of engagement which is what alleviates
the pain not gets you the pleasure from
the sense object there is no pleasure in
the sense object it's just objects of
perceptions which are neither
pleasurable nor dis pleasurable yet
you're feeling pleasurable on a carnival
and as well and that's why people like
to pursue central object if it's just
given but if it's a bit taking away
taking away taking away your pleasure
goes why would that happen if the
pleasure were truly in the object cuz
you haven't touched it yet how do you
know this is more of it yet there is
more of it in your mind so the desire
grows because the engagement towards
that direction grows could you
to basically go that way which means
that the the the extent of the prospect
of alleviating this also present
enduring pain grows so the pressure
grows because you yourself made it so
the way the butter describes the fine
strong sensuality like sites that you
can be conscious off with the I know
that you can't you you can become today
you could be conscious off chuckling the
area hmm so it's like it's basically bearing
hmm so it's like it's basically bearing
saying basically you are the the
sensuality is the possibility well Jack
Jack of in--yeah
in the pin the poly so it's it's sites
cog nine the big vertical translates its
ionizable by the cognizable could be
sure sure carbonized not that it is it's
all on the level of possibility yeah yes
cuz he's already starts there as soon as
you're subjected to pain and that's also
the world said the only way the
conclusion and those out of pain is
through sensuality which is not out of
pain but it's the only way he knows that
they closely resemble so dealing with
pain is what he thinks well no there is
there is a degree of alleviation if you
weren't so you wouldn't be pressured by
it either but it's that pursuit that
delighting the possibility of the
direction engaging with it kind of
magically gives the validity of oh yes
because I'm doing this that's why I'm
not subjected to this which you are
obviously still subjected sodomized you
wouldn't be going down the pursuit if
you're not subjected to the unpleasant
desire of it beforehand so that's the
gratification yeah seeing the
gratification is just seeing any
pleasure yeah yeah yes still with it and
that's why is the word of simplification
is on the level of the delight your
delighting and prospect so you have like
something secured you extend sort of
consuming it sure sure sure yeah you
prolong it yeah
because if you just do it oh it becomes
obvious how you cannot possibly pertain
to the domain you are acting from
so the extent of your scent sensual
cravings is directly determined by the
extent of your craving against the
painful feeling then you subtracted you
that's all it is
see so any like when you and again as I
said you always thought we don't like
the the owner you have to start with is
the order that's affecting with
ignorance you can't start things rightly so now
you can't start things rightly so now
okay yeah the lighting is in sensuality
is a problem but you're also my stop
delight well it's not quite a matter of
choice the lighting is a symptom of an
underlying assumption so in that case
when you are delighting in the prospect
of sensuality you want to then make sure
you include the delight and the prospect
of of sensual pursue that you mean
you're restraining against but the
prospect is still there so you want to
include the whole thing including the
future sense object within the container
of pain that's presently enduring not
left not right not before and certainly
not after it because that whole
assumption that I have a desire then
engage and I said like satisfy the
desire runs away no you just you you get
tired basically from running away from
the pain then you accept it and it cease
to hurt so what if you were to accept
the pain right away and removing the
middleman of central pursuit that cannot
possibly even pertain to the domain of
pain then you realize you'll be above
the pain even before the pain you can't
satisfy your desires but nobody denies
it after a degree of engagement with
your sensuality projected goals of your
desires you don't feel painful anymore why is
you don't feel painful anymore why is
that so the sense object remain
unchanged in a way like you haven't
truly consumed it to destroyed it it's
still there things you've been touching
even the food in a way it's still there
just now in the stomach as opposed to
the table so nothing has come out of the
material domain into your God
soon by the all-powerful sense herself
yet there is no pain now why is love you
discovered a hobo
how can you cover it all by five
how can you cover though when the domain
of senses cannot possibly pertain to the
domain of feelings what exchange stop
see you know you're not perceiving the
pain I knew it you're feeling it
what has changed that's you is it yeah
but you stopped pursuing it because it
doesn't hurt anymore the pressure is
gone why is that why is it that it
doesn't hurt any why did he hurt it in
the first place because you were just
subjected to thankful feeling no that's
not suffering ankle feeling is not
dukkha clearly to be free from painful
feeling so that's the only thing that
changed after a certain amount of
engagement with central object pursuit
of it in particular you stopped
resisting the unpleasant feeling in
itself and that's why you don't suffer
but pursuit of sense object had nothing
to do with you stop resisting it he was
basically a diversion and that's why
exactly sometimes if you keep engaging
with the pursuit of the sense objects it
becomes apparent that it cannot do
anything to the pain you'll feel it so
what you do that you double down you
triple down and that's all perception of
sense of proliferate because he has
nothing to do with the domain that you
are actually acting from and then yet
you go to the extremes just to hoping
that some of it will allow your mind to
take it as a successful project of
diversion basically so you don't know
how to stop crying in the feeling you're
just doing these random things hoping
that it will result in you at least
temporarily forgetting about resisting
the pain and that's why you have to stop
engaging centrality first even if you're
completely ignorant you have to start
practicing sense restraint first
because it's basically it's on the level
of a magical belief by diversion that
you know deep down is not and everybody
knows that I was saying that every time
you wanna go like I remember even way
before in my teens before I started
reading the goodies mess up you always
knew deep down you can't satisfy your
desires friends about it like you can't
say you can't help but pursuing them but
you know already you can't satisfy them
so the only thing that changes like
before the pursuit and after pursuit is
your own attitude in regard to what
you're already feeling what you've been
feeling all along that's it so you use
sense engagement to tire yourself out so
you can't create resistance you can't
maintain the resistance towards
unpleasant being during feeling and it
cease to be unpleasant it's not
suffering yeah but habitually anything
disagreeable is resisted and you make it
into suffering and yeah many times and
I'm sure everybody experienced that at
some point even after the combination of
your sense sensual satisfaction of
objects the mind still completely
unsatisfied and you want more the body
can't have more the body's fatigue
doesn't that they'd been scratched so
much it hurts yet the mental attitude of
stamina these are completely unchanged
and you just going mad basically with a
desire because you've been giving in to
that domain of off off sense pursuit
they had nothing to do this to and
that's the only way you know yes why are
you saying that when you've kind of gone
so gratifying it is eyes then after
would you feel sort of you feel
satisfied that the speaker that's
basically because through your acts
you've actually reduced craving
because there's no suffering well I
won't say you reduce that bit like
temporarily we'll stop doing it the
possibilities ability oh yeah no that's
true yes
resistance to suffering is craving yeah
you stop resisting when you tire
yourself out
survive I shake I am asking you are you
up
no that's why this gratification that's
how I start to this angle you like if
there is no gratification of calling it
it does it does gratify something and
you realize even the gratification has
nothing to do with sense objects has to
do with your own attitude towards your
own craving toward your own feeling
sorry which is already next to the
craving so so yes just to stretch eager
rich you are reducing you are reducing
craving what Sylvain Loosli making your
dependence on running away of pain even
even harder even stronger which means Oh
so through reducing this craving
actually I am fueling more like I'll be
more subjected to even more craving
later on because I need that yeah that's
I mean that's so first you have to stop
doing it and then you realize that even
the act of doing it were rooted in
actually oh it's simply because I don't
want this pain as in I but really resist
it well but it's not painful if I don't
resist it it's painful if I resist it
and then interfere with it means okay I
gave it validity next time I'll resist
it even more so what if I okay now I
stopped engaging with it stop
maintaining these wrong avenues of
trying to deal with it
stop scratching my itch what if I now to
endure the pain no let out of it and
then just stop resisting no try to get
rid of it that's another thing cuz if
you resist or like a super Suba becomes
for people getting rid of the the
sensual pain but yeah I must resist it
it doesn't exactly so the pain is there
if you tell if sensuality has a reason
that's what sensuality in its nature is
harassing that is the nature of sin so
to stay Horatio no no even before you
crave are say
the significance the implications of a
female body for a man or male body for a
woman of food for a hungry person the
implications are forceful even known or
required before school is felt
unpleasantly and then automatically
simultaneously an enlightened mind
resists any form of our pleasure
so you experience forceful perceptions
automatically are already resisting
which means automatically rotate the
delighting in them to get the freedom
for this resistance the you responsible
for that so another hunt will a mother
when he was with a woman took him her
you can stay in this room and then came
there and took her clothes off and tried
to basically sleep with him and the
synthesis and he just said cross leg
then was kind of became mindful of his
breathing and she was sort of bouncing
trying to get his attention then felt
embarrassed because he wasn't and then
dressed up and apologize I really first
time I read this suit I thought well why
would I don't even need to be mindful of
his breath like I thought out of hand
would be just completely blind but no he
was aware of the significance and that
significance is actually arising it's
unpleasant so he was mindful of his
breath just because he was subjected to
pain not because he tried to get rid of
it so okay with this harassment now
until it stops I'll just sort of be
mindful of my experience as a whole
while I'm being tortured
that's why dr. Paula Souter when he goes
home already on egami maybe even an hour
aunt and the father tells all his wives to
and the father tells all his wives to
dress up provocatively how they used to
how he used to like it and and they go
and start trying to seduce him he says
stop harassing this is harassing like
and it is and that's the nature of the
senses so you are harassed by your
senses being subjected to these forceful
sights sound smell taste touches again
like a dog he hears something he can't
help it he can't help you he wants to go
there now but you don't need to resist
that experience as a whole
level of harassment doesn't that apply
to basically girls right whether it's
painful or Pleasant
that's what if you were to undo the
craving on the absolute fundamental
level sexuality will be undone as well
it cannot possibly remain but more
practically you might have to address it
in itself go back to that painful
feeling yeah everything goes that's the
that's I keep saying it of the suitors
say that thinks converging feelings
always not sometimes not every other day
always which means direction your
motivation your perceptions basically
your moods where do they converge
converging how you're feeling right here
right now and that feeling indoors so
here you are can't stop thinking about a
central object where does it converge
converge or present enduring feeling of
discomfort that you're resisting you
want to get rid of it but not by anybody
means of distracting yourself in this
direction that's it and again
imagine what imagine being really really
hungry and you eat something
not even so tasty but it provides you
this great pleasure and then imagine
you're full to the point of feeling sick
and somebody brings something extremely
tasty and you're still sick there is no
pleasure in eating it again if the
pleasure were in these sense objects
there wouldn't be the case every time
you were to eat a pleasant thing it will
be felt pleasantly but when you are
hungry things they were not pleasant to
feel pleasantly and when you're not
hungry things that are pleasant feel
unpleasantly so what's in common to that
well it's in common today whatever your
senses are subjected to is in the way
forceful agreeable or disagreeable it
pushes significance implies requires you
pressures you but all of that will work
that whole domain of being pressured
implied pulled forced upon will work
only if you provide a basis for it and
the basis is I resisted discomfort and
that's that's how you then become pulled
and forced
and impressed you stop resisting the
comfort none of these things discomfort
none of these things cannot cannot
cannot can't possibly enter you or
certainly access there's any any
influence over you so the assumption we
have assumption is there's a prospect of
pleasure and I get I can get that more
precise assumption is assuming the
pleasure to be external to the pain
that's it
that's it so assuming pleasure to be
external to the to the present enduring
pain that's the assumption of sensuality
is that's already implied isn't it was
not connected is well that's the thing
assuming being external to the pain you
already form the external relationship
between the two then you can say it's
before it's after it's it's not
connected it's fully connected it's the
same it's different it's both it's
neither cuz you already assumed that
point is it so did it but basically it's
more than you want that you can you
assume that that pleasure can get rid of
that pain but that's because more
fundamentally you see it as external
from that pain and if you see that that
pleasure yeah it cannot possibly get rid
of that pain because it because it isn't
separate from my pain it's within this
with it's always within it in the same
sense you will stop maintaining the
notion of your master controller of the
five aggregates when you revisit any
notion you can have a positive sense of
self and master and controller is within
the five other days so any notion of
escape from this present enduring pain
any notion of pleasure any thought of up
tomorrow I'll experience this it's
within this so at that time to that
extent that is painful
which is why prospect of going away from
it is pleasant at the same time it's not
like again you don't have to wait
tomorrow to say no to yourself in regard
to sense objects you can already do it
right here right now in the level of the
mind that's why sensualities in the mind
that's why sensualities in the mind
the Buddha gave that simile like a man
lives completely immersed in sin Charlie
it's like a man in the river drench so
soaking wet and then he finds two sticks
and he wants to light the fire
well first he needs to step outside of
the river because he can't light the
fire what sticks but then even when he's
up on the shore he won't be able to
light a fire right away he needs to wait
for two sticks to dry for his hands to
dry and he said so it's like the man who
monks will be drove from sensuality but
their minds are still wet but when that
dries then you can enlighten the fire
basically means understanding this and
then yeah you can't get wet again
because it's burnt up but that's the
point so like now nothing you're just
kind of generally mindful you don't have
to necessarily context of sensual
assumptions and you have a thought or
something sensual the you are about to
be subjected or could be subjected to
the delight the extent of their delight
is the extent of your resistance to pain
nothing else the extent of their delight
is not in the object which you don't
have yet the extent that the light is
the extent of the pain basically that's
it and then yes the ones the skin feels
scratching it that's unpleasant so it's
the same act of the same sensuality that
was felt pleasant with first because of
an underlying condition so he put
underlying condition aside and act of
scratching is how how is it felt then
it's always unpleasant so experience of
sense objects is always unpleasant you
always harass by it and again that's
what I said Cal yeah exactly
the cow bean whether it leans on the
wall when the tree sits down stands it
being consumed but in seek the living
that on that surface and that is always
and that's why sensuality as an attitude
grows the more you engage with it the
more options you get from it because
it's again you always stays with you
never can never leave that domain there
is no outside
of the sense objects again we spoke
about it in regard to the phone but it's
the same principle if you're touching
something what are you experiencing the object you
what are you experiencing the object you
are touching or you experiencing the
experience of your hand touching
something exactly like so yet here you
are assuming that pleasure is contained
in particular inside of the particular
objects that you can't even enter with
your own senses let alone on the level
of the mind somehow to kind of transcend
this domain and enter this domain of
physicality the inconceivable desire
yeah the disturbance I desire you
satisfying it but simultaneous here yeah
then I'm going to satisfy it I'm gonna
keep this thing growing and it's not
gonna it's gonna disappear it yeah well
he's gonna disappear but by becoming
more and more apparent yeah we're
getting bigger
so when you do have again as I said
everybody starts from a wrong place
first when you do have a thought of
central object
don't try to negate it or deny it
please don't act towards it which would
be overly affirming it but down don't
try to deny it either allow it to endure
why because that's how you can discern a
context greater than the thought of
sensuality and this is the context
created we just described it so oh I did
it again I don't know I'm hungry and
there is a nice food in the table and
that is a delightful prospect I'm
delighting in it I'm not acting out of
it
so I'm trying to sing restraint but the
delight is there but if I don't go I
shouldn't feel this I shouldn't feel
like me oh now I still I'm trying to get
rid of it
first I try to go for it now I try to go
against it either way I want to get rid
of it so you must stop trying to get rid
of it so once you stop once you start
restraining and don't as I said overly
affirming to a physical action you do
have to learn how to lie to to endure
not mentally I don't I don't I don't
want because you didn't create it to
begin with you subtract it to it and you
only freedom from what your objective is
to fully understand it you can't
understand it if you keep denying it so
food is on the table I'm very hungry but
I'm restraining myself it hasn't been
offered I'm not gonna eat it now I have
to delight in my mind at the prospect of
eating it crossed with somebody coming
and offering when I'll eating in a song
how'd you free yourself from that or how
do you regain perspective in regard to
that direction of prospect as I said
would you be eating the food would you
be experiencing your mouth being
subjected to food and see that's the
context that you can easily be no but
you realize if you make an effort to not
ignore it it would actually shift the
emphasis from the food food food food -
oh these random senses that I was given
that subjected to are then subjected to
further things even if those things are
agreeable or disagreeable you stop
feeding them because now you're in the
right basis of not being careless in
regard to that
as I said can you experience the food
can you experience any sense object if
your senses are not their operating
living if there is no Sixth Sense base
present if the body is not there
functional you can't impossible so you
realize doesn't matter how much I forget
this it is the right order of things the
body comes first and S&S acity of the
six senses comes first yeah they are
only known through engagement with sense
objects but again I cannot abandon them
to go to sense objects because my only
formal relationship is with endeavors
they've relay to sense objects you have
to say so you stop assuming external to
your six senses again Papa Don I'm done
you stop assuming external to the to the
sense of five aggregates at ibadah I'm
done you stop assuming external to the
basically present enduring feeling means
you stop craving against the present
interior feeling rather against the odds
are against away from it for the Honda
it's always the same principle that's
why it's always super dominant